<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Stefan Fischer | Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine</title>
    <link>https://compai-lab.io/author/stefan-fischer/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://compai-lab.io/author/stefan-fischer/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Stefan Fischer</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://compai-lab.io/author/stefan-fischer/avatar_hu0b3bfded9873b98a8650d229e61b5476_259031_270x270_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Stefan Fischer</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/author/stefan-fischer/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five papers accepted at ISBI 2026 Main Conference</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/26_01_isbi_papers/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/26_01_isbi_papers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Covariance Descriptors Meet General Vision Encoders: Riemannian Deep Learning for Medical Image Classification&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Josef Mayr, Anna Reithmeir, Maxime Di Folco, Julia Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04190&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04190&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;LocBAM: Advancing 3D Patch-Based Image Segmentation by Integrating Location Context&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Donnate Hooft, Stefan Fischer, Cosmin Bercea, Jan Peeken, Julia Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14802&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14802&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Learning to Reason About Rare Diseases Through Retrieval-Augmented Agents&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ha Young Kim, Jun Li, Ana Beatriz Solana, Carolin Pirkl, Benedikt Wiestler, Julia Schnabel, Cosmin Bercea&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04720&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2511.04720&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Measuring and Aligning Abstraction in Vision-Language Models with Medical Taxonomies&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Ben Schaper1, Maxime Di Folco, Bernhard Kainz, Julia Schnabel, Cosmin Bercea&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14827&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2601.14827&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Uncertainty-guided Generation of Dark-field Radiographs&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Lina Felsner, Henriette Bast, Tina Dorosti, Florian Schaff, Franz Pfeiffer, Daniela Pfeiffer, Julia Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15859&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/2601.15859&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Integrating Location Context in Patch-based 3D Medical Image Segmentation</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_stefan/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_stefan/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep learning-based semantic segmentation is highly effective for detecting and segmenting tumors, anomalies, and organs-at-risk in medical imaging.
Unlike general computer vision tasks, medical imaging involves unique challenges, such as large 3D volumes from CT and MRI scans that require substantial computational resources.
To manage memory constraints, state-of-the-art models like nnUNet and SwinUNETR use patch-based methods, dividing 3D scans into smaller subvolumes.
The choice of patch size is crucial—large enough to retain meaningful anatomical context but small enough to fit within hardware limitations.
Networks must also infer the relative position of patches within the body to maintain spatial coherence in segmentation tasks.
Additional location information can be incorporated using image coordinates, physical scanner coordinates, or body-part regression tools.
This project aims to evaluate different methods for integrating location information into CNNs and Transformers for 3D medical image segmentation.
Techniques under consideration include coordinate images as additional channels, CoordConv layers, attention mechanisms, and positional embeddings.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Seven papers accepted at MICCAI 2024</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/miccai_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/miccai_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diffusion Models with Implicit Guidance for Medical Anomaly Detection&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Cosmin I. Bercea, Benedikt Wiestler, Daniel Rueckert, and Julia A. Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08464&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08464&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Physics-Informed Deep Learning for Motion-Corrected Reconstruction of Quantitative Brain MRI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Hannah Eichhorn, Veronika Spieker, Kerstin Hammernik, Elisa Saks, Kilian Weiss, Christine Preibisch, and Julia A. Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08298&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.08298&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Progressive Growing of Patch Size: Resource-Efficient Curriculum Learning for Dense Prediction Tasks&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Stefan M. Fischer, Lina Felsner, Daniel M. Lang, Richard Osuala, Johannes Kiechle, Jan C. Peeken, Julia A. Schnabel&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Interpretable Representation Learning of Cardiac MRI via Attribute Regularization&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Maxime Di Folco, Cosmin I. Bercea, Emily Chan, Julia A. Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08282&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2406.08282&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Towards Learning Contrast Kinetics with Multi-Condition Latent Diffusion Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Richard Osuala, Daniel M. Lang, Preeti Verma, Smriti Joshi, Apostolia Tsirikoglou, Grzegorz Skorupko, Kaisar Kushibar, Lidia Garrucho, Walter H. L. Pinaya, Oliver Diaz, Julia Schnabel, and Karim Lekadir&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13890&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2403.13890&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Data-Driven Tissue- and Subject-Specific Elastic Regularization for Medical Image Registration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Anna Reithmeir, Lina Felsner, Rickmer Braren, Julia A. Schnabel, Veronika A. Zimmer&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Self-Supervised k-Space Regularization for Motion-Resolved Abdominal MRI Using Neural Implicit k-Space Representation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Veronika Spieker, Hannah Eichhorn, Jonathan K. Stelter, Wenqi Huang, Rickmer F. Braren, Daniel Rückert, Francisco Sahli Costabal, Kerstin Hammernik, Claudia Prieto, Dimitrios C. Karampinos, Julia A. Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08350&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2404.08350&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Accepted at MELBA Journal</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/fischer_melba_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/fischer_melba_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stefan M. Fischer&amp;rsquo;s submission to the MICCAI2023 Lymph Node Quantification Challenge won the 3rd price.&lt;br&gt;
Therefore, the challenge team was invited for a presentation at MICCAI 2023 and to a Special Issue Submission at the MELBA Journal.
The journal submission &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Mask the Unknown: Assessing Different Strategies to Handle Weak Annotations in the MICCAI2023 Mediastinal Lymph Node Quantification Challenge&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is now available at MELBA.&lt;br&gt;
The paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.melba-journal.org/papers/2024:008.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
