<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ws25 | Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine</title>
    <link>https://compai-lab.io/tag/ws25/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://compai-lab.io/tag/ws25/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ws25</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://compai-lab.io/media/icon_hu790efcb2e4090d1e7a0ffec0a0776e8f_331139_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>ws25</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/tag/ws25/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>From General to Clinical - Adapting Foundation Models for Medical Images (IN2107)</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/teaching/seminar_foundation_models_ws25/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/teaching/seminar_foundation_models_ws25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://campus.tum.de/tumonline/ee/ui/ca2/app/desktop/#/slc.tm.cp/student/courses/950873177?$scrollTo=toc_overview&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Course details&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Foundation Models in Deep Learning for Medical Imaging
Deep learning models, from CNNs to Vision Transformers, have achieved impressive results for a variety of benchmarks and applications. However, real-world deployment, especially in medical imaging, remains challenging due to unseen variations in scanners, patient demographics, and pathological conditions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address this issue, recent work has focused on foundation models: large-scale models pretrained on diverse data using self- or weakly supervised learning. CLIP-based models learn general-purpose representations that transfer well to downstream tasks. For the context of medical imaging, specific fine-tuned models such as MedSAM and BiomedCLIP demonstrate strong potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, adapting foundation models to new domains or tasks often remains challenging. Although domain generalization and adaptation approaches exist, they may overfit or require target data. A recent paradigm, test-time adaptation, mitigates this by adapting alongside inference to unseen data. The techniques include adapting dynamically through model updates or prompt modifications that support more flexible deployment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This seminar will explore the foundations and capabilities of foundation models, with a focus on pretraining strategies, representational generalization, and efficient adaptation methods. We will examine state-of-the-art foundation models and discuss how they can be adapted to downstream tasks, especially in medical imaging, through techniques such as self-supervised learning, cross-domain transfer, and parameter-efficient tuning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Key topics to be covered include:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Introduction to Self Supervised Learning and Foundation Models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adaptation techniques to clinical applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples of Foundation models in medical imaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;State-of-the-art methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Requirements:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Background in image processing and machine learning/deep learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest in medical image analysis anf foundation models&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest in research&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please register via the TUM matching system: &lt;a href=&#34;https://matching.in.tum.de&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://matching.in.tum.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional information can be found &lt;a href=&#34;https://compai-lab.io/files/ws25-foundation-model-seminar-additional.pdf&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Intro slides: 















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://compai-lab.io/files/ws25-foundation-model-seminar.pdf&#34; alt=&#34;&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;/files/ws25-foundation-model-seminar.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/object&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
