<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Daniel M. Lang | Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine</title>
    <link>https://compai-lab.io/author/daniel-m.-lang/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://compai-lab.io/author/daniel-m.-lang/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Daniel M. Lang</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://compai-lab.io/author/daniel-m.-lang/avatar_hu30628bf96a1bbbf825de70e7e388d37a_614916_270x270_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>Daniel M. Lang</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/author/daniel-m.-lang/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three papers accepted at MICCAI 2025 Main Conference</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/25_06_miccai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 30 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/25_06_miccai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Temporal Neural Cellular Automata: Application to modeling of contrast enhancement in breast MRI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Daniel Lang, Richard Osuala, Veronika Spieker, Karim Lekadir,  Rickmer Braren, Julia Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18720&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2506.18720&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Influence of Classification Task and Distribution Shift Type on OOD Detection in Fetal Ultrasound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Chun Kit Wong, Anders Christensen, Cosmin Bercea, Julia Schnabel, Martin Tolsgaard, Aasa Feragen &lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Lightweight Data-Free Denoising for Detail-Preserving Biomedical Image Restoration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Tomáš Chobola, Julia Schnabel, Tingying Peng
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Zeyad Mahmoud presenting at Helmholtz Imaging Conference 2025</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/25_06_zeyad_conference_talk/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/25_06_zeyad_conference_talk/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Zeyad Mahmoud&amp;rsquo;s abstract has been selected for an oral presentation at the Helmholtz Imaging Conference 2025.
Zeyad presented his Master&amp;rsquo;s thesis research, titled &amp;ldquo;Unsupervised Temporal Diffusion-Based Interpolation for 4D CT&amp;rdquo;.
In this study, he investigated the ability of deep generative models, specifically diffusion models, for interpolating temporal 4D chest CT scans.
His work demonstrates how diffusion models can enable faster image acquisition and reduced radiation doses, while maintaining high temporal resolution, and therefore allow for precise dose planning for lung cancer patients.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Learning from Many - Domain Generalization for Medical Imaging</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_ambekar_domain_shift_25/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jun 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_ambekar_domain_shift_25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Deep learning achieves good performance when training and test data share similar distribution characteristics. However, for real-world scenarios—including medical imaging and natural scenes—significant domain shifts caused by diverse data characteristics and scanner settings often prevent models from generalizing to unseen domains. To address this at the model level, domain adaptation and domain generalization have emerged as potential solutions. Domain adaptation relies on access to target data to learn target representations, while domain generalization aims to learn invariant representations and obtain robust models using only source domains. Recently, a new paradigm called test-time adaptation further optimizes the model during online inference on the target domain to boost performance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these advancements, existing adaptation methods struggle with unique challenges in the target domain. These include class imbalance, category shifts within domains, reliance on unsupervised surrogate objectives, and non-i.i.d. assumptions that lead to error accumulation. Moreover, the scarcity of large annotated datasets limits the ability of models to learn meaningful representations for transfer. Recent studies also show that existing methods do not consistently improve performance in multi-source, real-world scenarios such as medical imaging.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This master’s thesis proposes new domain generalization and adaptation techniques to address these challenges. First, it will train models on multi-source data drawn from diverse distributions—different scanners, pathologies, and demographics. Next, it will explore existing domain generalization algorithms, analyzing the role of entropy minimization for optimizing model performance and the impact of feature alignment. Finally, it seeks to introduce novel contributions grounded in fundamental deep learning principles, with the goal of enhancing the adaptability and robustness of models across varied environments. The research outcomes are intended for publication in a relevant academic venue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start date ideally is June 2025. The thesis is offered by the Chair for Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine (Prof. Dr. Julia Schnabel) and supervised by Sameer Ambekar and Dr. Daniel Lang. If interested, please send your transcripts and a short motivation to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:sameer.ambekar@tum.de&#34;&gt;sameer.ambekar@tum.de&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:lang@helmholtz-munich.de&#34;&gt;lang@helmholtz-munich.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diffusion-Based Correspondences between Multimodal Medical Images</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_diffusion_features_anna/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_diffusion_features_anna/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Lesion tracking and image registration (finding the deformation between two images) are fundamental tasks in clinical practice for the diagnosis and monitoring of diseases. For this, establishing correct point correspondences between multiple images is essential.
Recent research in computer vision explores the use of diffusion model features for various image-based downstream tasks, including object detection, tracking, image editing, and classification, as well as the fusion of high-level semantic and low-level geometric features.
This thesis aims to adapt diffusion model-based features to medical images. In particular, the student will (i) perform literature research on the topic, (ii) explore SOTA correspondence matching techniques in the context of medical images, and (iii) develop new techniques for specific tasks on multimodal images, e.g., MR and CT. The project can be adapted to the student’s interests.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The start date ideally is February/March 2025. The thesis is offered by the Chair for Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine (Prof. Dr. Julia Schnabel) and supervised by Anna Reithmeir and Dr. Daniel Lang. If interested, please send your transcripts and a short motivation to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:anna.reithmeir@tum.de&#34;&gt;anna.reithmeir@tum.de&lt;/a&gt; and
&lt;a href=&#34;mailto:lang@helmholtz-munich.de&#34;&gt;lang@helmholtz-munich.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Self-supervised Learning in Medical Imaging - Theory and Applications​ (IN2107)</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/teaching/ssl_seminar/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/teaching/ssl_seminar/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://compai-lab.io/images/ssl.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Teaser&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More information will be provided during an introduction meeting scheduled at 12/02/2024 at 15h via Zoom:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://tinyurl.com/SSLMEDIMG&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://tinyurl.com/SSLMEDIMG&lt;/a&gt; , Meeting ID: 651 0606 0734 Passcode: 819595&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Self-supervised learning (SSL), described as &amp;ldquo;the dark matter of intelligence, overcomes the limitations of most learning methods, which require high-quality labelled data. This paradigm leverages large amounts of unlabeled data to learn meaningful representations through pretext tasks and enables models to generalise better and perform well on downstream tasks involving only a few labelled data. In medical imaging, image labels are usually very limited. Therefore, SSL is particularly valuable in this context. In a first step, the seminar will focus on the integration of state-of-the-art self-supervised learning techniques in computer vision. Next, those techniques will then be discussed in the context of medical problem settings featuring segmentation, detection, and classification. Selected material on methods and applications from the field of medical imaging will be covered. Basic problem formulations to recent advances will be discussed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This includes, but is not limited to:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Theory of Self-Supervised-Learning&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Examples of SSL data in medical imaging&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Clinical applications&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please register at: &lt;a href=&#34;https://matching.in.tum.de/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://matching.in.tum.de/&lt;/a&gt; or write an e-mail to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:maxime.di-folco@tum.de&#34;&gt;maxime.di-folco@tum.de&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the intro slides here:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;object data=&#34;/files/SSL_seminar.pdf&#34; type=&#34;application/pdf&#34; width=&#34;100%&#34; height=&#34;400&#34;&gt; 
&lt;/object&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Temporal Landmark Tracking on Medical Imaging</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_tracking_lang_reithmeir/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_tracking_lang_reithmeir/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Abstract:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though various learning-based computer vision methods have been developed for pixel tracking, motion estimation in video data depicts a challenging task. Part of the problem arises from the 3D-to-2D projection process that can lead to out-of-plane motion, which impedes long-range pixel trajectory estimation. In the medical domain, video data, i.e. fast magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) sequences, can be used for guidance during treatment. Specifically, in radiation therapy, contouring algorithms are used for tracking of the target volume supposed to receive the main radiation dose during treatment. Delineation can, for example, be performed with a U-Net architecture. However, such an approach only allows for identification of larger structures, while irregular movement can be subtle and localized. Landmark detection models are able to identify such localized regions between different representations of the same object. Furthermore, they are faster than semantic segmentation models, and therefore, allow for computer aided intervention during treatment. In this thesis, different state-of-the-art landmark and pixel tracking algorithms will be tested and further enhanced to identify movement on temporal imaging data of the lungs, i.e. 4D CT. Furthermore, ability of such landmarks to identify movement differing from a normal state, i.e. allowing for identification of anomalies, will be studied.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eleven papers accepted at MICCAI Workshops 2024</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/miccai_workshops_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 05 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/miccai_workshops_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Selective Test-Time Adaptation using Neural Implicit Representations for Unsupervised Anomaly Detection [Best Paper Award]&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Sameer Ambekar, Julia Schnabel, and Cosmin I. Bercea. &lt;br&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03306&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2410.03306&lt;/a&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;MedEdit: Counterfactual Diffusion-based Image Editing on Brain MRI&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Malek Ben Alaya, Daniel M. Lang, Benedikt Wiestler, Julia A. Schnabel, and Cosmin I. Bercea&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.15270&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.15270&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Unsupervised Analysis of Alzheimer’s Disease Signatures using 3D Deformable Autoencoders&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Mehmet Yigit Avci, Emily Chan, Veronika Zimmer, Daniel Rueckert, Benedikt Wiestler, Julia A. Schnabel, and Cosmin I. Bercea&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.03863&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.03863&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;On Differentially Private 3D Medical Image Synthesis with Controllable Latent Diffusion Models&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Deniz Daum; Richard Osuala; Anneliese Riess; Georgios Kaissis; Julia A. Schnabel; Maxime Di Folco&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16405&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.16405&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Graph Neural Networks: A suitable alternative to MLPs in latent 3D medical image classification?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Johannes Kiechle, Daniel M. Lang, Stefan M. Fischer, Lina Felsner, Jan C. Peeken, Julia A. Schnabel&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17219&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;http://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17219&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;General Vision Encoder Features as Guidance in Medical Image Registration&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Fryderyk Kögl, Anna Reithmeir, Vasiliki Sideri-Lampretsa, Ines Machado, Rickmer Braren, Daniel Rückert, Julia A Schnabel, Veronika A Zimmer&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13311&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.13311&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Language Models Meet Anomaly Detection for Better Interpretability and Generalizability&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Jun Li, Su Hwan Kim, Philip Müller, Lina Felsner, Daniel Rueckert, Benedikt Wiestler, Julia A.Schnabel, and Cosmin I. Bercea&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.07622v2&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2404.07622v2&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Self-Supervised Image Registration Approach for Measuring Local Response Patterns in Metastatic Ovarian Cancer&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Inês P. Machado, Anna Reithmeir, Fryderyk Kogl, Leonardo Rundo, Gabriel Funingana, Marika Reinius, Gift Mungmeeprued, Zeyu Gao, Cathal McCague, Eric Kerfoot, Ramona Woitek, Evis Sala, Yangming Ou, James Brenton, Julia Schnabel, Mireia Crispin&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17114&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.17114&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Diffusion Models for Unsupervised Anomaly Detection in Fetal Brain Ultrasound&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Hanna Mykula, Lisa Gasser, Silvia Lobmaier, Julia A. Schnabel, Veronika Zimmer, and Cosmin I. Bercea&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.15119&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2407.15119&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Enhancing the Utility of Privacy-Preserving Cancer Classification using Synthetic Data&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Richard Osuala, Daniel M. Lang, Anneliese Riess, Georgios Kaissis, Zuzanna Szafranowska, Grzegorz Skorupko, Oliver Diaz, Julia A. Schnabel, Karim Lekadir&lt;br&gt;
(&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12669&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://arxiv.org/abs/2407.12669&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Complex-valued Federated Learning with Differential Privacy and MRI Applications&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;br&gt;
Anneliese Riess, Alexander Ziller, Stefan Kolek, Daniel Rueckert, Julia Schnabel, Georgios Kaissis &lt;br&gt;
([link will be available soon])&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Paper Accepted at MELBA Journal</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/fischer_melba_24/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/fischer_melba_24/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Stefan M. Fischer&amp;rsquo;s submission to the MICCAI2023 Lymph Node Quantification Challenge won the 3rd price.&lt;br&gt;
Therefore, the challenge team was invited for a presentation at MICCAI 2023 and to a Special Issue Submission at the MELBA Journal.
The journal submission &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Mask the Unknown: Assessing Different Strategies to Handle Weak Annotations in the MICCAI2023 Mediastinal Lymph Node Quantification Challenge&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; is now available at MELBA.&lt;br&gt;
The paper is available &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.melba-journal.org/papers/2024:008.html&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Five papers accepted at MICCAI 2023 workshops</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/iml_miccai_workshops/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/iml_miccai_workshops/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Five papers have been accepted for publication at workshops associated with the 26th International Conference on Medical Image Computing and Computer Assisted Intervention, MICCAI 2023, which will be held from October 8th to 12th 2023 in Vancouver, Canada.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Interested to hear more about our work? Then join us at the following workshops:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Veronika Spieker will be at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://dgm4miccai.github.io/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;DGM4&lt;/a&gt; workshop to talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2308.08830&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Neural Implicit Representations for Abdominal MR Reconstruction&lt;/a&gt; on October 8, at 10:25.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hannah Eichhorn presents her work on physics-aware motion simulation for T2*-weighted MRI at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://2023.sashimi-workshop.org/program/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;SASHIMI&lt;/a&gt; workshop on October 8, at 14:40. Check out the &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.10987&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt; for more information!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Maxime Di Folco presents at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://stacom.github.io/stacom2023/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;STACOM&lt;/a&gt; workshop on October 12, at 11:15 the work of Josh Stein on &amp;ldquo;Sparse annotation strategies for segmentation of short axis cardiac MRI&amp;rdquo;  (&lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2307.12619&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;preprint&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cosmin Bercea will talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/pdf/2308.13861.pdf&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Bias in Unsupervised Anomaly Detection&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://faimi-workshop.github.io/2023-miccai/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;FAIMI&lt;/a&gt; workshop on October 12, at 2:50 PDT.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Lang will talk about &lt;a href=&#34;https://arxiv.org/abs/2303.05861&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Anomaly Detection in Non-Contrast Enhanced Breast MRI&lt;/a&gt; at the &lt;a href=&#34;https://caption-workshop.github.io/miccai2023/#Workshop%20sessions&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;CaPTion&lt;/a&gt; workshop on October 12.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
