<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Natascha Niessen | Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine</title>
    <link>https://compai-lab.io/author/natascha-niessen/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://compai-lab.io/author/natascha-niessen/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Natascha Niessen</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://compai-lab.io/author/natascha-niessen/avatar_hu9af5966520882a14db9b53f5642a7350_123885_270x270_fill_q75_lanczos_center.jpg</url>
      <title>Natascha Niessen</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/author/natascha-niessen/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>Three abstracts accepted at 2026 ISMRM &amp; ISMRT Annual Meeting.</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/26_02_ismrm_abstracts/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Feb 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/26_02_ismrm_abstracts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Three abstracts from our group have been accepted at the 2026 ISMRM &amp;amp; ISMRT Annual Meeting in Cape Town, South Africa:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ha Young Kim will present her work “Radiomics and Biomarker-Based Analysis of Arterial Spin Labelling MRI in Alzheimer’s Disease and non-AD Dementia” in a presentation on Monday, May 11 at 8.20 am SAST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natascha Niessen will present her work &amp;ldquo;Highly accelerated 3D MPnRAGE meets implicit neural representation (INR) reconstruction&amp;rdquo; as a digital poster on Thursday, May 14 at 2.40 pm SAST.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vincent Wohlfahrt will present his work &amp;ldquo;Automated Segmentation of Individual Cerebral Perfusion Territories from Vessel-Selective MRI by Deep Learning&amp;rdquo; as a digital poster on Tuesday, May 12 at 5 pm SAST.
&lt;br/&gt;&lt;br/&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiparametric (TI-TE) MRI sequence adaptation and implicit neural representation (INR)-based reconstruction</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_niessen_reconstruction_26/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 07 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/vacancies/msc_niessen_reconstruction_26/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h3 id=&#34;problem-statement&#34;&gt;Problem statement&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Multiparametric MRI sequences allow for the acquisition of images with varying tissue contrast
within a single scan. The resulting multiparametric images can be used to extract quantitative
information on tissue microstructure. To make such multiparametric sequences feasible for
clinical routine, the usually very long scan times need to be shortened e.g. through
undersampling in k-space. However, this comes with challenges for the reconstruction. In
general, advanced reconstruction techniques such as compressed sensing or deep learning-based approaches (1) can enable the acquisition of high-quality images despite the
acceleration. For multiparametric MRI sequences very high accelerations can be achieved by
leveraging redundant anatomical information e.g. through joint reconstruction with an implicit
neural representation (INR) network (2).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;goals&#34;&gt;Goals&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This project aims to extend an MPnRAGE (3) (multiple inversion times, TI) acquisition and
reconstruction framework by adding an echo time (TE) dimension. The first part of the project
will involve modifying the existing MPnRAGE sequence, including iterative improvements on the
scanner. The second part of the project will focus on adapting the INR-based reconstruction for
the multiparametric (TI-TE) data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The student will benefit from:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Guidance from both MRI and AI experts in a collaborative, interdisciplinary research
setting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hands on experience with the MRI scanner and coding.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Opportunity to contribute to ongoing research and potential publication in medical
imaging journals or conferences.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;requirements&#34;&gt;Requirements&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;1 year master thesis (such as in BEMP MSc).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Prior experience and good understanding of MRI physics and machine learning.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Very good programming skills in Python (PyTorch) and Matlab.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Experience in using Unix systems (Linux, macOS Terminal).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Interest in MRI and hands-on experience with the MRI scanner.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Intended starting date:&lt;/strong&gt; 01 February 2026&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;application&#34;&gt;Application&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Please send an email, involving a CV, a current transcript of records, and a brief statement on
why you are interested in the project, to &lt;a href=&#34;mailto:natascha.niessen@tum.de&#34;&gt;natascha.niessen@tum.de&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;affiliation&#34;&gt;Affiliation&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Prof. Dr. Julia Schnabel
Informatik 32 - Lehrstuhl fur Computational Imaging and AI in Medicine
Supervision: Natascha Niessen, Dr.-Ing. Lina Felsner&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;references&#34;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Deep learning for accelerated and robust MRI reconstruction. Heckel R, Jacob M, Chaudhari
A, Perlman O, Shimron E. s.l. : MAGMA. 2024;37(3):335-368.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;INR Meets Multi-contrast MRI Reconstruction. Niessen N, Pirkl CM, Solana AB, Eichhorn H,
Spieker V, Huang W, Sprenger T, Menzel MI, Schnabel JA. s.l. : Reconstruction and Imaging
Motion Estimation, and Graphs in Biomedical Image Analysis: First International Workshop,
RIME 2025, and 7th International Workshop, GRAIL 2025, pp. 23-33, Springer-Verlag, Berlin,
Heidelberg, 2025, 2025.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;MPnRAGE: A technique to simultaneously acquire hundreds of differently contrasted
MPRAGE images with applications to quantitative T1 mapping. Kecskemeti S, Samsonov A,
Hurley SA, Dean DC, Field A, Alexander AL. Magn Reson Med. 2016 Mar;75(3):1040-53.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Best presentation award at MICCAI-RIME Workshop 2025</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/25_09_niessen_award/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/25_09_niessen_award/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;1st place in the Best Presentation Award at the MICCAI-RIME Workshop 2025 goes to Natascha Niessen for her work titled “INR Meets Multi-Contrast MRI Reconstruction.” The paper presents a method to significantly accelerate multi-contrast brain MRI scans without compromising image quality, contributing to the PREDICTOM - IHI project (&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.predictom.eu/&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;https://www.predictom.eu/&lt;/a&gt;) focused on early Alzheimer’s detection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;















&lt;figure  &gt;
  &lt;div class=&#34;d-flex justify-content-center&#34;&gt;
    &lt;div class=&#34;w-100&#34; &gt;&lt;img src=&#34;https://compai-lab.io/images/MICCAI2025-overview.png&#34; alt=&#34;Overview&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; data-zoomable /&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Four abstracts accepted at 2025 ISMRM &amp; ISMRT Annual Meeting</title>
      <link>https://compai-lab.io/post/ismrm25/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://compai-lab.io/post/ismrm25/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Four abstracts from our group have been accepted at the &lt;strong&gt;2025 ISMRM &amp;amp; ISMRT Annual Meeting&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hannah Eichhorn will present her work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Leveraging Acquisition Knowledge to Enhance Robustness of Physics-Informed Motion Correction for T2* Quantification&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; as an oral power pitch on Monday, &lt;strong&gt;12 May 2025 at 4 pm HAST&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hannah Eichhorn will additionally present her work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Assessing the Influence of Preprocessing on the Agreement of Image Quality Metrics with Radiological Evaluation in the Presence of Motion&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; as an oral power pitch on Monday, &lt;strong&gt;12 May 2025 at 4 pm HAST&lt;/strong&gt;. Hannah&amp;rsquo;s abstract received a MAGNA CUM LAUDE Merit Award.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natascha Niessen will present her work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Probing the sparsity of the MPnRAGE sequence through subspace compression&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; as a digital poster on Thursday, &lt;strong&gt;15 May 2025 at 2:15 pm HAST&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ha Young Kim will present her work &amp;ldquo;&lt;em&gt;Deep learning enabled fast free-breathing stack-of-stars multiparameter mapping for fully quantitative analysis of prostate carcinoma&lt;/em&gt;&amp;rdquo; as a digital poster on Monday, &lt;strong&gt;12 May 2025 at 5 pm HAST&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
